Henry White Edgerton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry White Edgerton Papers 1910-1970 1929-1966
MSS36038
Edgerton, Henry White, 1888-1970
2,000 items
8 containers
3.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Jurist, lawyer, and educator. Correspondence, memoranda, writings, case files, reports, notes, pamphlets, lists, newspaper clippings, and printed matter, relating mainly to White's career as a law professor and judge.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Arant, Herschel Whitfield, 1887-1941--Correspondence.; Edgerton, Henry White, 1888-1970.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Graustein, Archibald--Correspondence.; Harris, Rufus C. (Rufus Carrollton), 1897-1988--Correspondence.; Miller, Justin, 1888-1973--Correspondence.; Pound, Roscoe, 1870-1964--Correspondence.; Robinson, J. J.--Correspondence.; Waite, John Barker, 1882-1967--Correspondence.
Organizations
Association of American Law Schools.; Cornell University.; United States. Court of Appeals (District of Columbia Circuit); United States. National Recovery Administration.
Subjects
Civil rights.; Courts--Washington (D.C.); Criminology.; Law--Study and teaching.; Law--United States.; Separation of powers--United States.
Places
United States--Politics and government.
Occupations
Educators.; Judges.; Lawyers.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Henry White Edgerton, jurist, lawyer, and educator, were given to the Library of Congress in 1970 and 1972 by his wife, Alice Durand Edgerton.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry White Edgerton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1888, Oct. 20 Born, Rush Center, Kans.
1905 1907 Attended University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wis.
1910 A.B., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1910 1911 Attended law school, University of Paris, Paris, France
1913 Married Alice Durand
1914 LL.B, Harvard Law School, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. Attorney, Davis, Kellogg & Severance, St. Paul, Minn.
1915 1916 Attorney, Warner, Warner & Stackpole, Boston, Mass.
1916 1918 Acting assistant professor of law, Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1918 1921 Attorney, Ropes, Gray, Boyden & Perkins, Boston, Mass
1921 1928 Professor of law, George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1928 1929 Visiting professor of law, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1929 1937 Professor of law, Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1934 1935 Special assistant to the attorney general, Antitrust Division, Department of Justice, Washington, D.C.
1937 1970 Judge, United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, Washington, D.C.; chief judge, 1955-1968; senior status, 1963-1970
1970, Feb. 23 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Henry White Edgerton (1888-1970) range from 1910 to 1970, with the bulk of the material dating from 1929 to 1966. The papers document primarily Edgerton's activities as a law professor at Cornell University, 1929-1937, and as a judge for the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, 1937-1970. The collection is organized into a subject file and an addition.
Pertaining chiefly to Edgerton's career as a law professor and his writings, the subject file includes correspondence, drafts of articles, letters to the editor, notes, pamphlets, reports, newspaper clippings, and printed matter. Topics featured are civil liberties, criminology, law school curriculum, and the roles of the three branches of government. Edgerton's ideas on curriculum and criminology are revealed in correspondence with deans and professors at law schools on matters relating to his activities in the Association of American Law Schools. Among the correspondents are Herschel Whitfield Arant, Rufus C. Harris, Justin Miller, Roscoe Pound, J. J. Robinson, and John Barker Waite. Also included is correspondence with Felix Frankfurter and others relating to an article by Edgerton's about the incidence of judicial supremacy over Congress, although these files do not contain any drafts or working papers.
The only correspondence covering an appreciable span of years, 1930-1969, is with Archibald Graustein, an attorney with the Boston law firm of Ropes, Gray, Boyden & Perkins and president of the International Paper Company. The letters, chiefly from Graustein, touch on the opinions of Edgerton in various court cases, personal, family, and business matters, and occasionally on contemporary affairs. Included are references to Edgerton's activities while on the bench of the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit.
Other correspondence documents Edgerton's affiliations with civil liberties organizations and his interest in several trials in which they were involved. There are also several manuscripts written while he was a special attorney in the Department of Justice relating to the National Recovery Administration, and a few items pertaining to three letters to editors by Edgerton. There is no documentation of Edgerton's activities as a private attorney and little information on his classroom lectures.
The addition to the collection, 1944-1967, consists primarily of case files documenting Edgerton's tenure as a judge for the Court of Appeals. The case files include memoranda, opinions, orders, and judgments.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by name of person or organization, topic, or type of material.
Container List
- Subject file (Box 1)
  - Academic freedom, 1932 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1932-1938 (Box 1)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (Box 1)
    - Annual reports, 1926-1937 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1932-1937 (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets, 1919, 1928-1937 (Box 1)
  - American Law Institute, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Association of American Law Schools (Box 1)
    - General, 1930-1933 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Advertising and Soliciting, 1936-1937 (Box 1)
    - Joint Committee on the Improvement of Criminal Justice, 1931-1934 (Box 1)
    - Round Table on Criminal Law, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Special Committee on the Teaching of Professional Ethics, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Civil liberties, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Competition, wastes of railroads, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Constitution, proposed amendments, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y. (Box 2)
    - Class oration, 1910 (Box 2)
    - Heidelberg celebration, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Criminology (Box 2)
    - Miscellany, 1930-1934 (Box 2)
    - Reformatories, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Vengeance, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Free speech, Ives law repeal, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Faculty of Political and Social Science, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Graustein, Archibald, 1930-1969 (Box 2)
  - Incidence of Judicial Supremacy over Congress, correspondence (includes correspondence from Felix Frankfurter), 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Imprisonment for costs, circa 1930-1970 (Box 2)
  - Labor injunctions, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - Labor unions and antitrust acts, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Lawless law enforcement, 1932 (Box 2)
  - National Bail Fund, 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - National Recovery Administration (Box 2)
    - General, 1933-1935 (Box 2)
    - United States v. Perkins, 1934 (Box 2)
    - United States v. Sley, undated (Box 2)
      - Abstracts (Box 2)
      - Brief (Box 2)
  - Neutrality, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1932-1936 (Box 2)
  - New York (state), district constitutional delegate, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Political Prisoners, International Committee for, 1936 (Box 3)
  - President of the United States, emergency powers, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Printed matter (Box 3)
    - Government Printing Office, publication lists, 1927-1930 (Box 3)
    - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., 1919-1926 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1930-1940 (Box 3)
  - Public utilities, public ownership of, 1928-1932 (Box 3)
  - Regimentation, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Sacco-Vanzetti case, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Scottsboro case, 1933-1936 (Box 3)
  - Selective Service System, draft questionnaire form, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Supreme Court, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Civil rights (Box 3)
    - Proposal (Box 3)
    - Revamping (Box 3)
  - "Third degree" interrogations, 1932-1937 (Box 3)
  - University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill., Committee on Graduate Work, circa 1928 (Box 3)
- Addition (Box 4)
  - Case file (Box 4)
    - Air Line Pilots Ass'n Int'l v. National Mediation Bd. (Box 4)
    - American Nat'l Red Cross v. Holtman (Box 4)
    - Armour & Co. v. Freeman (Box 4)
    - "A" miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Blocker v. United States (Box 4)
    - Blunt v. United States (Box 4)
    - "B" miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Coleman v. United States (Box 4)
    - Contempt of Congress cases (Box 4)
    - "C" miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Deans v. United States (Box 4)
    - "D-E" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Far East Conference v. Federal Maritime Comm'n (Box 4)
    - Fay v. Miller (Box 4)
    - Florida Gulfcoast Broadcasters v. Federal Communications Comm'n (Box 5)
    - Frady v. United States (Box 5)
    - Franco v. United States (Box 5)
    - Frigillana v. United States (Box 5)
    - "F" miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Gager v. Seidel (Box 5)
    - Georgetown College, application of the president of (Box 5)
    - Goldsmith v. United States (Box 5)
    - Grabois v. Grosner (Box 5)
    - "G" miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Hellenic Lines Ltd. v. Moore (Box 5)
    - Hutcherson v. United States (Box 5)
    - "H-K" miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - Lake v. Cameron (Box 6)
    - Landa v. Austin (Box 6)
    - In re Laughlin (Box 6)
    - Lee v. United States (Box 6)
    - "L" miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - McDonald v. United States (Box 6)
    - Milk Drivers' Union Local 753 v. National Labor Relations Bd. (Box 6)
    - "M" miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - National Labor Relations Bd. v. Rice Lake Creamery Co. (Box 6)
    - "N-O" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Peninsula Corp. v. United States (Box 7)
    - Perry v. Perry (Box 7)
    - "P-R", (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Safarik v. Udall (Box 7)
    - South Fla. TV Corp. v. Federal Communications Comm'n (Box 7)
    - "S-U", (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Vinson v. Einbinder (Box 7)
    - "V" miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - West Tex. Utils. Co. v. National Labor Relations Bd. (Box 8)
    - White v. Schwartz (Box 8)
    - "W-Y", (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Miscellany (Box 8)
    - Agendas (Box 8)
    - Judicial Council of the District of Columbia, minutes 1944, May (Box 8)
    - List of witnesses, 1953, Dec. 15-17 (Box 8)
    - Memoranda and letters, 1937-1955 (Box 8)
    - Memoranda for en banc cases, 1962-1966 (Box 8)
    - Senate bill 684, proposed creation of an Administrative Court of the United States (Box 8)
    - Printed matter (Box 8)
    - Clippings (Box 8)